<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<story>
    <title>The Robber Bridegroom</title>
    <author>Jacob and Wilhelm Grimm</author>
    <p>Once upon a time there was a miller who had a <descriptor type="positive" gender="female">beautiful daughter.</descriptor> When she came of age he
        wished that she was provided for and well married. He thought, "If a respectable suitor
        comes and asks for her hand in marriage, <action agency="passive" gender="male" willingness="eager">I will give her to him."</action></p>
    <p>Not long afterward a <descriptor type="positive" gender="male">suitor came who appeared to be very rich,</descriptor> and because the miller could
        find no fault with him, <action agency="passive" gender="male" willingness="eager">he promised his daughter to him.</action></p>
    <p><descriptor type="negative" gender="female">The girl, however, did not like him as much as a bride should like her bridegroom.</descriptor> <descriptor type="negative" gender="male">She did
        not trust him, and whenever she saw him or thought about him, she felt within her heart a
        sense of horror.</descriptor></p>
    <p>One time he said to <action agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="hesitant">her, "You are engaged to marry me, but you have never once paid me a
        visit."</action></p>
    <p>The girl replied, "I don't know where your house is."</p>
    <p>Then the bridegroom said, "My house is out in the dark woods."</p>
    <p><action agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="hesitant">Looking for an excuse, she said that she would not be able to find the way there.</action></p>
    <p>The bridegroom said, "Next Sunday you must come out to me. I have already invited guests. <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">I
        will make a trail of ashes, so that you can find your way through the woods."</action></p>
    <p>When Sunday came, and it was time for the girl to start on her way, she became frightened,
        although she herself did not know exactly why. In order to mark the path, <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="hesitant">she filled both
        her pockets full of peas and lentils.</action> At the entrance of the forest there was a trail of
        ashes, which she followed, but at every step she threw a couple of peas to the ground, to
        the right and to the left. She walked almost the whole day until she came to the middle of
        the woods, where it was the darkest, and there stood a solitary house. She did not like it,
        because it looked so dark and sinister. She went inside, but no one was there. It was
        totally quiet.</p>
    <p>Suddenly a voice called out:</p>
    <p>Turn back, turn back, you <descriptor type="positive" gender="female">young bride.</descriptor></p>
    <p><descriptor type="negative" gender="male">You are in a murderer's house.</descriptor></p>
    <p>The girl looked up and saw that the voice came from a bird, which was hanging in a cage on
        the wall. It cried out again:</p>
    <p>Turn back, turn back, you <descriptor type="positive" gender="female">young bride.</descriptor></p>
    <p><descriptor type="negative" gender="male">You are in a murderer's house.</descriptor></p>
    <p>Then the <descriptor type="positive" gender="female">beautiful bride</descriptor> went from one room to another, <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="hesitant">walking through the whole house, but
        it was entirely empty, and not a human soul was to be found. Finally she came to the cellar.</action>
        A <descriptor type="negative" gender="female">very old woman</descriptor> was sitting there shaking her head.</p>
    <p>"Could you tell me," said the girl, "if my bridegroom lives here?"</p>
    <p>"Oh, you poor child," replied the old woman, "where did you come from? You are in a
        <descriptor type="negative" gender="male">murderer's den.</descriptor> You think you are a bride soon to be married, but it is <descriptor type="negative" gender="male">death that you will
        be marrying.</descriptor> Look, they made me put a large kettle of water on the fire. When they have
        captured you, <descriptor type="negative" gender="male">they will chop you to pieces without mercy, cook you, and eat you, for they
            are cannibals.</descriptor> If I do not show you compassion and save you, you are doomed."</p>
    <p>With this the <descriptor type="negative" gender="female">old woman</descriptor> led her behind a large barrel where she could not be seen.</p>
    <p>"Be quiet as a mouse." she said. "Do not make a sound or move, or all will be over with you.
        <action agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="eager">Tonight when the robbers are asleep we will escape. I have long waited for an
        opportunity."</action></p>
    <p>This had scarcely happened when the <descriptor type="negative" gender="male">godless band</descriptor> came home. <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">They were dragging with them
        another maiden.</action> They were drunk and paid no attention to her screams and sobs.</p>
    <p><action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">They gave her wine to drink,</action> three glasses full, one glass of white, one glass of red, and
        one glass of yellow, which caused her heart to break. <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">Then they ripped off her fine clothes,
        laid her on a table, chopped her beautiful body in pieces and sprinkled salt on it.</action> The poor
        bride behind the barrel trembled and shook, for she saw well what fate the robbers had
        planned for her.</p>
    <p>One of them noticed a gold ring on the murdered girl's little finger. Because it did not come
        off easily, <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">he took an ax and chopped the finger off,</action> but it flew into the air and over the
        barrel, falling right into the bride's lap. The robber took a light and looked for it, but
        could not find it.</p>
    <p>Then another one said, "Did you look behind the large barrel?"</p>
    <p>But the <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">old woman cried out, "Come and eat. You can continue looking in the morning. That
        finger won't run away from you."</action></p>
    <p>Then the robbers said, "The old woman is right." They gave up their search and sat down to
        eat. <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">The old woman poured a sleeping-potion into their wine,</action> so that they soon lay down in
        the cellar and fell asleep, snoring.</p>
    <p><action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">When the bride heard them snoring she came out from behind the barrel, and had to step over
        the sleepers, for they lay all in rows on the ground. She was afraid that she might awaken
        one of them, but God helped her, and she got through safely.</action></p>
    <p>The <description type="negative" gender="female">old woman</description> went upstairs with her, opened the door, and <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">they hurried out of the murderer's
        den as fast as they could.</action></p>
    <p>The wind had blown away the trail of ashes, but the peas and lentils had sprouted and grown
        up, and showed them the way in the moonlight. <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">They walked all night, arriving at the mill
        the next morning. Then the girl told her father everything, just as it had happened.</action></p>
    <p>When the wedding day came, <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">the bridegroom appeared.</action> The miller had invited all his relatives
        and acquaintances. As they sat at the table, each one was asked to tell something. <action agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="hesitant">The bride
        sat still and said nothing.</action></p>
    <p>Then the bridegroom said to the bride, "Come, sweetheart, don't you know anything? Tell us
        something, like the others have done."</p>
    <p>She answered:</p>
    <p>Then I will tell about a dream. I was walking alone through the woods, when finally I came to
        a house. Inside there was not a single human soul, but on the wall there was a bird in a
        cage. It cried out:</p>
    <p>Turn back, turn back, you <description type="positive" gender="female">young bride.</description></p>
    <p>You are in a <description type="negative" gender="male">murderer's house.</description></p>
    <p>Then it cried out the same thing again. Darling, it was only a dream. Then I went through all
        the rooms. They were all empty, and there was something so eerie in there. Finally I went
        down into the cellar, and there sat a <description type="negative" gender="female">very old woman,</description> shaking her head. I asked her, "Does
        my bridegroom live in this house?"</p>
    <p>She answered, "Alas poor child, you have gotten into a <description type="negative" gender="male">murderer's den. Your bridegroom does
        live here, but he intends to chop you to pieces and kill you, and then he intends to cook
        you and eat you."</description></p>
    <p>Darling, it was only a dream. After that the <description type="negative" gender="female">old woman</description> <action agency="active" gender="female" willinggness="eager">hid me behind a large barrel.</action> I had
        scarcely hidden myself there when the robbers came home, <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">dragging a girl with them. They
        gave her three kinds of wine to drink:</action> white, red, and yellow, which caused her heart to
        stop beating. Darling, it was only a dream. <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">After that they took off her fine clothes, and
            chopped her <description type="positive" gender="female">beautiful body</description> to pieces on a table, then sprinkled salt on it.</action> Darling, it was
        only a dream. Then one of the robbers saw that there was still a ring on her ring finger.
        Because it was hard to get the ring off, <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">he took an ax and chopped off the finger.</action> The
        finger flew through the air behind the large barrel, and fell into my lap. And here is the
        finger with the ring.</p>
    <p><action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">With these words she pulled out the finger and showed it to everyone who was there.</action></p>
    <p><description type="negative" gender="male">The robber, who had during this story become as white as chalk,</description> <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">jumped up and tried to
        escape,</action> but the guests held him fast, and turned him over to the courts. <action agency="active" gender=female" willingness="eager">Then he and his
        whole band were executed for their shameful deeds.</action></p>
    <source>Source: Jacob and Wilhelm Grimm, Der Räuberbräutigam, Kinder- und Hausmärchen
        (Children's and Household Tales -- Grimms' Fairy Tales), final edition (Berlin, 1857), no.
        40.</source>
    <translator>Translated by D. L. Ashliman. © <year>2001-2002.</year></translator>
</story>
