<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fairytale>
    <metadata>
        <title>Hans-My-Hedgehog (1857)</title>
    </metadata>
    <body>
    <p>Once upon a time there was a peasant who had money and land enough, but as <descriptor
            type="positive" gender="male">rich</descriptor> as he was, there was still something
            <descriptor type="negatve" gender="male">missing from his happiness</descriptor>: He had
        no children with his wife. Often when he went to the city with the other peasants, they
        would mock him and ask him why he had no children. He finally became <descriptor
            type="negative" gender="male">angry</descriptor>, and when he returned home, he said, "I
        will have a child, even if it is a hedgehog."</p>
    <p>Then his wife had a baby, and the top half was a hedgehog and the bottom half a boy. When she
        saw the baby, she was <descriptor type="negative" gender="female">horrified</descriptor> and
        said, "Now see what you have wished upon us!"</p>
    <p>The man said, "It cannot be helped. The boy must be baptized, but we cannot ask anyone to be
        his godfather."</p>
    <p>The woman said, "And the only name that we can <action agency="active" gender="female"
            willingness="hesitant">give him is Hans-My-Hedgehog</action>."</p>
    <p>When he was baptized, the pastor said, "Because of his quills he cannot be given an ordinary
        bed." So they put a little straw behind the stove and laid him in it. And he could not drink
        from his mother, for he would have stuck her with his quills. He <action agency="passive"
            gender="male" willingness="neutral">lay there behind the stove for eight years</action>,
        and his father <action agency="passive" gender="male" willingness="neutral">grew tired of
            him</action>, and thought, "if only he would die." But he did not die, but just lay
        there.</p>
    <p>Now it happened that there was a fair in the city, and the peasant wanted to go. He <action
            agency="active" gender="male" willingness="neutral">asked</action> his wife what he
        should bring her.</p>
    <p>"A little meat, some bread rolls, and things for the household," she said. Then he <action
            agency="active" gender="male" willingness="neutral">asked</action> the servant girl, and
        she wanted a pair of slippers and some fancy stockings.</p>
    <p>Finally, he also <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="neutral">said</action>,
        "Hans-My-Hedgehog, what would you like?"</p>
    <p>"Father," he said, "bring me some bagpipes."</p>
    <p>When the peasant <action agency="passive" gender="male" willingness="neutral">returned
            home</action> he gave his wife what he had brought for her, meat and bread rolls. Then
        he gave the servant girl the slippers and fancy stockings. And finally he went behind the
        stove and gave Hans-My-Hedgehog the bagpipes.</p>
    <p>When Hans-My-Hedgehog had them, he said, "Father, go to the blacksmith's and have my
        cock-rooster shod, then I will ride away and never again come back." The father was happy to
        get rid of him, so he <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">had his
            rooster shod</action>, and when it was done, Hans-My-Hedgehog <action agency="active"
            gender="male" willingness="eager">climbed</action> on it and rode away. He <action
            agency="active" gender="male" willingness="neutral">took</action> pigs and donkeys with
        him, to tend in the forest.</p>
    <p>In the forest the rooster flew into a tall tree with him. There he <action agency="passive"
            gender="male" willingness="neutral">sat</action> and <action agency="passive"
            gender="male" willingness="neutral">watched</action> over the donkeys and the pigs. He
            <action agency="passive" gender="male" willingness="neutral">sat there for
            years</action>, until finally the herd had grown large. His father knew nothing about
        him. While <action agency="passive" gender="male" willingness="neutral">sitting</action> in
        the tree, he <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="neutral">played his
            bagpipes</action> and made beautiful music.</p>
    <p>One day a king came by. He was lost and heard the music. He was amazed to hear it, and
            <action agency="passive" gender="male" willingness="eager">sent a servant</action> to
        look around and see where it was coming from. He <action agency="active" gender="male"
            willingness="neutral">looked here</action> and there but only saw a little animal
        sitting high in a tree. It looked like a rooster up there with a hedgehog sitting on it
        making the music.</p>
    <p>The king <action agency="passive" gender="male" willingness="neutral">said to the
            servant</action> that he should ask him why he was sitting there, and if he knew the way
        back to his kingdom. Then Hans-My-Hedgehog <action agency="active" gender="male"
            willingness="neutral">climbed</action> down from the tree and told him that he would
        show him the way if the king would <action agency="passive" gender="male"
            willingness="neutral">promise</action> in writing to give him the first thing that
        greeted him at the royal court upon his arrival home.</p>
    <p>The king thought, "I can do that easily enough. Hans-My-Hedgehog cannot understand writing,
        and I can put down what I want to."</p>
    <p>Then the king took pen and ink and <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager"
            >wrote something</action>, and after he had done so, Hans-My-Hedgehog <action
            agency="active" gender="male" willingness="neutral">showed him the way</action>, and he
        arrived safely at home. His daughter saw him coming from afar, and was so overjoyed that she
            <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">ran</action> to meet him and
            <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">kissed</action> him. He
        thought about Hans-My-Hedgehog and told her what had happened, that he was supposed to have
        promised the first thing that greeted him to a strange animal that rode a rooster and made
        beautiful music. But instead he had written that this would not happen, for Hans-My-Hedgehog
        could not read. The princess was <descriptor type="positive" gender="female"
            >happy</descriptor> about this, and said that it was a good thing, for she would not
        have gone with him in any event.</p>
    <p>Hans-My-Hedgehog tended the donkeys and pigs, was of <descriptor type="positive"
            gender="male">good cheer</descriptor>, and sat in the tree <action agency="passive"
            gender="male" willingness="neutral">blowing on his bagpipes</action>.</p>
    <p>Now it happened that another king came this way with his servants and messengers. He too
            <action agency="passive" gender="male" willingness="neutral">got lost</action> and did
        not know the way back home because the forest was so large. He too heard the beautiful music
        from afar, and <action agency="passive" gender="male" willingness="eager">asked one of his
            messengers</action> to go and see what it was and where it was coming from. The
        messenger <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="neutral">ran</action> to the
        tree where he saw Hans-My-Hedgehog astride the cock-rooster. The messenger asked him what he
        was doing up there.</p>
    <p>"I am <action agency="passive" gender="male" willingness="neutral">tending</action> my
        donkeys and pigs. What is it that you want?" replied Hans-My-Hedgehog.</p>
    <p>The messenger said that they were lost and could not find their way back to their kingdom,
        and asked him if he could not show them the way.</p>
    <p>Then Hans-My-Hedgehog <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="neutral"
            >climbed</action> down from the tree with his rooster and told the old king that he
        would show him the way if he would give him the thing that he first met at home before the
        royal castle.</p>
    <p>The king said yes and <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="hesitant">signed a
            promise</action> to Hans-My-Hedgehog.</p>
    <p>When that was done, Hans-My-Hedgehog rode ahead on his rooster <action agency="active"
            gender="male" willingness="neutral">showing them the way</action>, and the king safely
        reached his kingdom. When the king arrived at his court there was great joy. Now he had an
        only daughter who was <descriptor type="positive" gender="fenale">very
            beautiful</descriptor>. She <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager"
            >ran out to him</action>, <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager"
            >threw her arms around his neck</action> and <action agency="active" gender="female"
            willingness="eager">kissed</action> him, and was ever <descriptor type="positive"
            gender="female">so happy</descriptor> that her old father had returned.</p>
    <p>She <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">asked</action> him where he
        had been during his long absence, and he <action agency="active" gender="male"
            willingness="neutral">told her</action> how he had lost his way and almost not made it
        home again, but that as he was making his way through a great forest he had come upon a half
        hedgehog, half human astride a rooster sitting in a tall tree and making beautiful music who
        had shown him the way, but whom he had promised whatever first met him at the royal court,
        and it was she herself, and he was terribly <descriptor type="negative" gender="male"
            >sorry</descriptor>.</p>
    <p>But she <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="hesitant">promised</action> that
        she would go with him when he came, for the <action agency="passive" gender="female"
            willingness="eager">love</action> of her old father.</p>
    <p>Hans-My-Hedgehog <action agency="passive" gender="male" willingness="neutral">tended his
            pigs</action>, and the pigs had more pigs, until there were so many that the whole
        forest was full. Then Hans-My-Hedgehog let his father know that they should empty out all
        the stalls in the village, because he was <action agency="active" gender="male"
            willingness="neutral">coming</action> with such a large herd of pigs that everyone who
        wanted to would be able to take part in the slaughter.</p>
    <p>It saddened the father to hear this, for he thought that Hans-My-Hedgehog had long since
        died. But Hans-My-Hedgehog <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="neutral"
            >mounted his cock-rooster</action>, <action agency="active" gender="male"
            willingness="neutral">drove the pigs</action> ahead of himself into the village, and
            <action agency="passive" gender="male" willingness="neutral">had them
        butchered</action>. What a slaughter! What a commotion! They could hear the noise two hours
        away!</p>
    <p>Afterward Hans-My-Hedgehog said, "Father, <action agency="passive" gender="male"
            willingness="neutral">have my cock-rooster shod</action> a second time at the
        blacksmith's. Then I will <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="neutral">ride
            away</action> and not come back again as long as I live." So the father had the <action
            agency="active" gender="male" willingness="neutral">cock-rooster shod</action>, and was
        happy that Hans-My-Hedgehog was not coming back.</p>
    <p>Hans-My-Hedgehog <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="neutral">rode</action>
        into the first kingdom. The king had <action agency="passive" gender="male"
            willingness="neutral">ordered</action> that if anyone should approach who was carrying
        bagpipes and riding on a rooster, that he should be shot at, struck down, and stabbed, to
        prevent him from entering the castle. Thus when Hans-My-Hedgehog rode up, they <action
            agency="active" gender="male" willingness="neutral">attacked</action> him with bayonets,
        but he <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="neutral">spurred his
            rooster</action> on, flew over the gate and up to the king's window. Landing there, he
            <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="neutral">shouted</action> to him, to
        give him what he had promised, or it would cost him and his daughter their lives.</p>
    <p>Then the king <action agency="passive" gender="male" willingness="hesitant">told the
            princess</action> to go out to him, in order to save his life and her own as well. She
            <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="hesitant">put on a white
            dress</action>, and her father gave her a carriage with six horses, magnificent
        servants, money, and property. She <action agency="active" gender="female"
            willingness="hesitant">climbed</action> aboard and Hans-My-Hedgehog <action
            agency="passive" gender="male" willingness="eager">took his place beside her</action>
        with his rooster and bagpipes. They said farewell and drove off.</p>
    <p>The king thought that he would never see them again. However, it did not go as he thought it
        would, for when they had traveled a short distance from the city, Hans-My-Hedgehog <action
            agency="active" gender="male" willingness="neutral">pulled off her beautiful
            clothes</action> and <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="neutral">stuck
            her</action> with his quills until she was bloody all over. "This is the reward for your
        deceit. Go away. I do not want you." With that he sent her back home, and she was
            <descriptor type="negative" gender="female">cursed</descriptor> as long as she
        lived.</p>
    <p>Hans-My-Hedgehog, astride his cock-rooster and carrying his bagpipes, <action agency="active"
            gender="male" willingness="neutral">rode on</action> to the second kingdom where he had
        also helped the king find his way. This one, in contrast, had ordered that if anyone looking
        like Hans-My-Hedgehog should arrive, he should be saluted and brought to the royal castle
        with honors and with a military escort.</p>
    <p>When the princess saw him she was <descriptor type="negative" gender="female"
            >horrified</descriptor>, because he looked so <descriptor type="negative" gender="male"
            >strange</descriptor>, but she thought that nothing could be done about it, because she
        had <action agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="neutral">promised</action> her
        father to go with him. She <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="neutral"
            >welcomed</action> Hans-My-Hedgehog, and they were married. Then he was taken to the
        royal table, and she <action agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="neutral">sat next
            to him</action> while they ate and drank, and they were married.</p>
    <p>That evening when it was time to go to bed, she was <descriptor type="negative"
            gender="female">afraid</descriptor> of his quills, but he told her to have no fear, for
        he would not hurt her. He <action agency="passive" gender="male" willingness="neutral">told
            the old king</action> to have four men keep watch by their bedroom door. They should
        make a large fire. He said that he would take off his hedgehog skin after going into the
        bedroom, and before getting into bed. The men should immediately pick it up and <action
            agency="active" gender="male" willingness="neutral">throw it</action> into the fire, and
        then stay there until it was completely consumed by the fire.</p>
    <p>When the clock struck eleven, he went into the bedroom, took off the hedgehog skin, and
            <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="neutral">laid</action> it down by the
        bed. The men <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="neutral">rushed in</action>,
            <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="neutral">grabbed it</action>, and
            <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="neutral">threw it</action> into the
        fire, and as soon as the fire consumed it, he was redeemed, and he lay there in bed entirely
        in the shape of a human. But he was as black as coal, as though he had been charred. The
        king sent for his physician, who washed him with good salves and balms. Then he became white
        and was a <descriptor type="positive" gender="male">handsome</descriptor>
        <descriptor type="positive" gender="male">young</descriptor>
        <descriptor type="positive" gender="male">gentleman</descriptor>.</p>
    <p>When the princess saw what had happened, she was <descriptor type="positive" gender="female"
            >overjoyed</descriptor>, and they got up and ate and drank. Now their wedding was
        celebrated for real, and Hans-My-Hedgehog <action agency="passive" gender="male"
            willingness="neutral">inherited</action> the old king's kingdom.</p>
    <p>Some years later he <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="neutral">traveled with
            his wife</action> to his father, and said that he was his son. But the father said that
        he did not have a son. He had had one, but he had been born with quills like a hedgehog and
        had gone off into the world. Then he said that he was the one, and the old father <action
            agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">rejoiced</action> and returned with
        him to his kingdom.</p>
    <lg>
        <l>My tale is done,</l>
        <l>And has gone</l>
        <l>To Gustchen's home.</l>
    </lg>
    </body>
    <ending happy_ending="true"/>
</fairytale>
