<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../grimm_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<fairytale>
    <metadata>
        <title>Iron Heinrich (1857)</title>
    </metadata>
    <body>
        <p>In olden times, when wishing still did some good, there lived a king whose daughters were
            all <descriptor type="positive" gender="female">beautiful</descriptor>, but the youngest
            was <descriptor type="positive" gender="female">so beautiful</descriptor> that the sun
            itself, who, indeed, has seen so much, marveled every time it shone upon her face. In
            the vicinity of the king's castle there was a large, dark forest, and in this forest,
            beneath an old linden tree, there was a well. In the heat of the day the princess would
            go out into the forest and <action agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="eager"
                >sit</action> on the edge of the cool well. To pass the time she would take a golden
            ball, <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="neutral">throw</action> it
            into the air, and then <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="neutral"
                >catch</action> it. It was her favorite plaything.</p>
        <p>Now one day it happened that the princess's golden ball did not fall into her hands, that
            she held up high, but instead it fell to the ground and rolled right into the water. The
            princess <action agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="neutral"
                >followed</action> it with her eyes, but the ball disappeared, and the well was so
            deep that she could not see its bottom. Then she began to <action agency="passive"
                gender="female" willingness="neutral">cry</action>. She <action agency="passive"
                gender="female" willingness="neutral">cried</action> louder and louder, and she
            could not console herself.</p>
        <p>As she was thus <action agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="neutral"
                >lamenting</action>, someone called out to her, "What is the matter with you,
            princess? Your crying would turn a stone to pity."</p>
        <p>She <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="neutral">looked</action> around
            to see where the voice was coming from and saw a frog, who had stuck his thick, ugly
            head out of the water. "Oh, it's you, old water-splasher," she said. "I am crying
            because my golden ball has fallen into the well."</p>
        <p>"Be still and stop crying," answered the frog. I can <action agency="active"
                gender="male" willingness="hesitant">help</action> you, but what will you give me if
            I bring back your plaything?"</p>
        <p>"Whatever you want, dear frog," she <action agency="active" gender="female"
                willingness="neutral">said</action>, "my clothes, my pearls and precious stones, and
            even the golden crown that I am wearing."</p>
        <p>The frog <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="neutral">answered</action>,
            "I do not want your clothes, your pearls and precious stones, nor your golden crown, but
            if you will <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">love</action> me
            and <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">accept</action> me as a
            companion and playmate, and let me <action agency="passive" gender="male"
                willingness="eager">sit</action> next to you at your table and <action
                agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">eat</action> from your golden
            plate and <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">drink</action> from
            your cup and <action agency="passive" gender="male" willingness="eager">sleep</action>
            in your bed, if you will <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="neutral"
                >promise</action> this to me, then I'll <action agency="active" gender="male"
                willingness="hesitant">dive</action> down and bring your golden ball back to
            you."</p>
        <p>"Oh, yes," she said, "I <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager"
                >promise</action> all of that to you if you will just bring the ball back to me."
            But she <action agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="hesitant"
            >thought</action>, "What is this <descriptor type="negative" gender="male"
                >stupid</descriptor> frog trying to say? He just <action agency="passive"
                gender="male" willingness="neutral">sits</action> here in the water with his own
            kind and <action agency="passive" gender="male" willingness="neutral">croaks</action>.
            He cannot be a companion to a human."</p>
        <p>As soon as the frog <action agency="passive" gender="male" willingness="neutral"
                >heard</action> her say "yes" he <action agency="active" gender="male"
                willingness="eager">stuck</action> his head under and <action agency="active"
                gender="male" willingness="eager">dove</action> to the bottom. He <action
                agency="active" gender="male" willingness="neutral">paddled</action> back up a short
            time later with the golden ball in his mouth and <action agency="active" gender="male"
                willingness="neutral">threw</action> it onto the grass. The princess was <action
                agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="eager">filled</action> with joy when
            she saw her beautiful plaything once again, picked it up, and ran off.</p>
        <p>"Wait, wait," <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">called</action>
            the frog, "take me along. I cannot run as fast as you." But what did it help him, that
            he <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="neutral">croaked</action> out
            after her as loudly as he could? She paid no attention to him, but instead <action
                agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">hurried</action> home and soon
                <action agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="neutral">forgot</action> the
            poor frog, who had to return again to his well.</p>
        <p>The next day the princess was <action agency="passive" gender="female"
                willingness="neutral">sitting</action> at the table with the king and all the people
            of the court, and was <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="neutral"
                >eating</action> from her golden plate when something came creeping up the marble
            steps: plip, plop, plip, plop. As soon as it reached the top, there came a <action
                agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">knock</action> at the door, and a
            voice called out, "Princess, <descriptor type="positive" gender="female"
                >youngest</descriptor>, open the door for me!"</p>
        <p>She <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">ran</action> to see who
            was outside. She <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager"
                >opened</action> the door, and the frog was <action agency="passive" gender="male"
                willingness="neutral">sitting</action> there. <descriptor type="negative"
                gender="female">Frightened</descriptor>, she <action agency="active" gender="female"
                willingness="eager">slammed</action> the door shut and <action agency="passive"
                gender="female" willingness="eager">returned</action> to the table. The king saw
            that her heart was pounding and asked, "My child, why are you <descriptor
                type="negative" gender="female">afraid</descriptor>? Is there a giant outside the
            door who wants to get you?"</p>
        <p>"Oh, no," she answered. "it is a <descriptor type="negative" gender="male"
                >disgusting</descriptor> frog."</p>
        <p>"What does the frog want from you?"</p>
        <p>"Oh, father dear, yesterday when I was sitting near the well in the forest and <action
                agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="neutral">playing</action>, my golden
            ball fell into the water. And because I was <action agency="passive" gender="female"
                willingness="neutral">crying </action>so much, the frog brought it back, and because
            he insisted, I <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="hesitant"
                >promised</action> him that he could be my companion, but I didn't think that he
            could leave his water. But now he is just outside the door and wants to come in."</p>
        <p>Just then there came a second <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager"
                >knock</action> at the door, and a voice <action agency="active" gender="male"
                willingness="eager">called</action> out:</p>
        <lg>
            <l><descriptor type="positive" gender="female">Youngest</descriptor> daughter of the
                king,</l>
            <l>Open up the door for me,</l>
            <l>Don't you know what yesterday,</l>
            <l>You said to me down by the well?</l>
            <l><descriptor type="positive" gender="female">Youngest</descriptor> daughter of the
                king,</l>
            <l>Open up the door for me.</l>
        </lg>
        <p>The king said, "What you have promised, you must keep. Go and let the frog in."</p>
        <p>She went and <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="hesitant"
                >opened</action> the door, and the frog hopped in, then <action agency="active"
                gender="male" willingness="neutral">followed</action> her up to her chair. He
                <action agency="passive" gender="male" willingness="neutral">sat</action> there and
                <action agency="passive" gender="male" willingness="neutral">called</action> out,
            "Lift me up next to you."</p>
        <p>She hesitated, until finally the king <action agency="active" gender="male"
                willingness="hesitant">commanded</action> her to do it. When the frog was seated
            next to her he said, "Now <action agency="passive" gender="female"
                willingness="hesitant">push</action> your golden plate closer, so we can eat
            together."</p>
        <p>She did it, but one could see that she did not want to. The frog <action agency="passive"
                gender="male" willingness="eager">enjoyed</action> his meal, but for her every
                <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="hesitant">bite</action> stuck
            in her throat. Finally he said, "I have eaten all I want and am tired. Now carry me to
            your room and make your bed so that we can go to sleep."</p>
        <p>The princess began to <action agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="neutral"
                >cry</action> and was afraid of the cold frog and did not dare to even touch him,
            and yet he was supposed to sleep in her beautiful, clean bed.</p>
        <p>The king <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="neutral">became
                angry</action> and said, "You should not despise someone who has helped you in time
            of need."</p>
        <p>She <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="hesitant">picked him up</action>
            with two fingers, <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="hesitant"
                >carried</action> him upstairs, and <action agency="passive" gender="female"
                willingness="hesitant">set</action> him in a corner. As she was <action
                agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="hesitant">lying in bed</action>, he
            came <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="neutral">creeping</action> up to
            her and said, "I am tired, and I want to sleep as well as you do. Pick me up or I'll
            tell your father."</p>
        <p>With that she became bitterly angry and <action agency="active" gender="female"
                willingness="eager">threw him against the wall</action> with all her might. "Now you
            will have your peace, you <descriptor type="negative" gender="male"
                >disgusting</descriptor> frog!"</p>
        <p>But when he fell down, he was not a frog, but a prince with <descriptor type="positive"
                gender="male">beautiful</descriptor>
            <descriptor type="positive" gender="male">friendly</descriptor> eyes. And he was now,
            according to her father's will, her dear companion and husband. He told her how he had
            been enchanted by a wicked witch, and that she alone could have <action agency="active"
                gender="female" willingness="neutral">rescued him</action> from the well, and that
            tomorrow they would go together to his kingdom. Then they fell asleep.</p>
        <p>The next morning, just as the sun was waking them, a carriage pulled up, drawn by eight
            horses. They had white ostrich feathers on their heads and were outfitted with chains of
            gold. At the rear stood the young king's servant, faithful Heinrich. Faithful Heinrich
            had been so <action agency="passive" gender="male" willingness="neutral">saddened by his
                master's transformation</action> into a frog that he had had to place three iron
            bands around his heart to keep it from bursting in grief and sorrow. The carriage was to
            take the king back to his kingdom. <descriptor type="positive" gender="male"
                >Faithful</descriptor> Heinrich <action agency="active" gender="male"
                willingness="eager">lifted</action> them both inside and took his place at the rear.
            He was filled with joy over the redemption. After they had gone a short distance, the
            prince heard a crack from behind, as though something had broken.</p>
        <p>He turned around and said, "Heinrich, the carriage is breaking apart."</p>
        <lg>
            <l>No, my lord, the carriage it's not,</l>
            <l>But one of the bands surrounding my heart,</l>
            <l>That suffered such great pain,</l>
            <l>When you were sitting in the well,</l>
            <l>When you were a frog.</l>
        </lg>
        <p>Once again, and then once again the prince heard a cracking sound and thought that the
            carriage was breaking apart, but it was the bands springing from <descriptor
                type="positive" gender="male">faithful</descriptor> Heinrich's heart because his
            master was now redeemed and happy.</p>
        <ending happy_ending="true"/>
    </body>
</fairytale>
