<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fairytale>
    <metadata>
        <title>Frau Holle (1857)</title>
        <author>Jacob and Wilhelm Grimm</author>
    </metadata>
    <body>
    <p>A widow had two daughters, the one was <descriptor type="positive" gender="female"
            >beautiful</descriptor> and <descriptor type="positive" gender="female"
            >industrious</descriptor>, the other <descriptor type="negative" gender="female"
            >ugly</descriptor> and <descriptor type="negative" gender="female">lazy</descriptor>.
        She greatly <action agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="neutral">favored</action>
        the <descriptor type="negative" gender="female">ugly</descriptor>, <descriptor
            type="negative" gender="female">lazy</descriptor> girl, because she was her own
        daughter. And the other one had to do all the work, and be the <descriptor type="negative"
            gender="female">Cinderella</descriptor> of the house.</p>
    <p>Every day the <descriptor type="negative" gender="female">poor</descriptor> girl had to
            <action agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="neutral">sit</action> by a well,
        next to the highway, and <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="hesitant">spin
            so much</action> that her fingers bled. Now it happened that one day the reel was
        completely bloody, so she <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="neutral"
            >dipped</action> it in the well, to wash it off, but it <action agency="passive"
            gender="female" willingness="neutral">dropped</action> out of her hand and fell in. She
            <action agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="neutral">cried</action>, <action
            agency="active" gender="female" willingness="neutral">ran to her stepmother</action>,
        and told her of the mishap. She <action agency="active" gender="female"
            willingness="neutral">scolded her</action> so sharply, and was so <descriptor
            type="negative" gender="female">merciless</descriptor> that she said, "Since you have
        let the reel fall in, you must fetch it out again."</p>
    <p>Then the girl went back to the well, and did not know what to do. <descriptor type="negative"
        gender="female">Terrified</descriptor>, she <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="hesitant">jumped into the well</action> to get the reel. She
        lost her senses. And when she <action agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="neutral">awoke</action> and came to herself again, she was in a beautiful meadow
        where the sun was shining, and there were many thousands of flowers. She walked across this
        meadow and came to an oven full of bread. The bread called out, "Oh, take me out. Take me
        out, or I'll burn. I've been thoroughly baked for a long time." So she stepped up to it, and
        with a baker's peel <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="neutral">took everything out</action>, one loaf after the other.</p>
    <p>After that she walked further and came to a tree laden with apples. "Shake me. Shake me. We
        apples are all ripe." cried the tree. So she <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="neutral">shook the tree</action> until the apples fell as though
        it were raining apples. When none were left in the tree, she <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="neutral">gathered them</action> into a pile, and
        then continued on her way.</p>
    <p>Finally she came to a small house. An old woman was peering out from inside. She had very
        <descriptor type="negative"
            gender="female">large teeth</descriptor>, which <descriptor type="negative"
                gender="female">frightened</descriptor> the girl, and she wanted to run away. But the old woman called
        out to her, "Don't be afraid, dear child. Stay here with me, and if you do my housework in
        an orderly fashion, it will go well with you. Only you must take care to make my bed well
        and shake it diligently until the feathers fly, then it will snow in the world. I am Frau
        Holle."</p>
    <p>Because the old woman spoke so <descriptor type="negative"
        gender="female">kindly</descriptor> to her, the girl took heart, agreed, and started in her
        service. The girl took care of everything to Frau Holle's satisfaction and always <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="neutral">shook her
        featherbed vigorously</action> until the feathers flew about like snowflakes. Therefore she had a
        good life with her: no angry words, and boiled or roast meat every day.</p>
    <p>Now after she had been with Frau Holle for a time, she became <descriptor type="negative"
        gender="female">sad</descriptor>. At first she did not know
        what was the matter with her, but at last she determined that it was <descriptor type="negative"
            gender="female">homesickness</descriptor>. Even
        though she was many thousands of times better off here than at home, still she had a
        yearning to return. Finally she said to the old woman, "I have such a longing for home, and
        even though I am very well off here, I cannot stay longer. I must go up again to my own
        people."</p>
    <p>Frau Holle said, "I am pleased that you long for your home again, and because you have served
        me so <descriptor type="positive"
            gender="female">faithfully</descriptor>, I will take you back myself." With that she took her by the hand and <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="neutral">led
        her</action> to a large gate.</p>
    <p>The gate was opened, and while the girl was standing under it, an immense rain of gold fell,
        and all the gold stuck to her, so that she was completely covered with it. "This is yours
        because you have been so <descriptor type="positive"
            gender="female">industrious</descriptor>," said Frau Holle, and at the same time she gave her
        back the reel which had fallen into the well.</p>
    <p>With that the gate was closed and the girl found herself above on earth, not far from her
        mother's house. And as she entered the yard the rooster, sitting on the well, cried:</p>
    <lg>
        <l>Cock-a-doodle-doo,</l>
        <l>Our golden girl is here anew.</l>
    </lg>
    <p>Then she went inside to her mother, and as she arrived all covered with gold, she was well
        received, both by her mother and her sister. The girl told all that had happened to her, and
        when the mother heard how she had come to the great wealth, she wanted to <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="neutral">achieve</action> the same
        fortune for the other, the <descriptor type="negative"
            gender="female">ugly</descriptor> and <descriptor type="negative"
                gender="female">lazy</descriptor> daughter. She made her go and <action agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="neutral">sit</action> by the well and
        spin. And to make her reel bloody, the lazy girl pricked her fingers and shoved her hand
        into a thorn bush. Then she threw the reel into the well, and <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">jumped in herself</action>.</p>
    <p>Like the other girl, she too came to the beautiful meadow and walked along the same path.
        When she came to the oven, the bread cried again, "Oh, take me out. Take me out, or else
        I'll burn. I've been thoroughly baked for a long time."</p>
    <p>But the lazy girl answered, "As if I would want to get all dirty," and <action agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="neutral">walked away</action>.</p>
    <p>Soon she came to the apple tree. It cried out, "Oh, shake me. Shake me. We apples are all
        ripe."</p>
    <p>But she answered, "Oh yes, one could fall on my head," and with that <action agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="eager">she walked on</action>.</p>
    <p>When she came to Frau Holle's house, she was not afraid, because she had already heard about
        her <descriptor type="negative"
            gender="female">large teeth</descriptor>, and she immediately began to work for her. On the first day she forced
        herself, was <descriptor type="positive"
            gender="female">industrious</descriptor>, and obeyed Frau Holle, when she said something to her, because she
        was thinking about all the gold that she would give her. But on the second day she already
        began to be <descriptor type="negative"
            gender="female">lazy</descriptor>, on the third day even more so, and then she didn't even want to get up in
        the morning. She did not make the bed for Frau Holle, the way she was supposed to, and she
        did not shake it until the feathers flew. Frau Holle soon became tired of this and dismissed
        her of her duties. This was just what the lazy girl wanted, for she thought that she would
        now get the rain of gold.</p>
    <p>Frau Holle <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="neutral">led her</action> too to the gate. She stood beneath it, but instead of gold, a large kettle
        full of pitch spilled over her. "That is the reward for your services," said Frau Holle, and
        closed the gate.</p>
    <p>Then the lazy girl went home, entirely covered with pitch. As soon as the rooster on the well
        saw her, he cried out:</p>
    <lg>
        <l>Cock-a-doodle-doo,</l>
        <l>Our dirty girl is here anew.</l>
    </lg>
    <p>And the pitch stuck fast to her, and did not come off as long as she lived.</p>
</body>
    <ending happy_ending="true"/>
</fairytale>
