<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<story>

    <title>Hansel and Gretel</title>
    <p>Next to a great forest there lived a <description type="negative" gender="male">poor woodcutter</description> who had come upon such hard times that
        he could scarcely provide daily bread for his wife and his two children, Hansel and Gretel.
        <action agency="passive" gender="male" willingness="eager">Finally he could no longer even manage this,</action> and he did not know where to turn for help.</p>
    <p><action agency="passive" gender="male" willingness="eager">One evening as he was lying in bed worrying about his problems,</action> his wife said to him,
        "Listen, man, early tomorrow take the two children, give each of them a little piece of
        bread, then lead them into the middle of thickest part of the woods, make a fire for them,
        and leave them there, for we can no longer feed them."</p>
    <p><action agency="passive" gender="male" willingness="eager">"No, woman,"</action> said the man, "I cannot bring myself to abandon my own children to wild animals
        that would quickly tear them to pieces."</p>
    <p>"If you don't do it," said the woman, "all of us will starve together," <action agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="eager">and she gave him no
        peace until he said yes.</action></p>
    <p>The two children were still awake from hunger and heard everything that the mother had said
        to the father.</p>
    <p>Gretel thought that <action agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="neutral">she was doomed and began to cry pitifully,</action> but Hansel said, "Be quiet,
        Gretel, and don't worry. I know what to do."</p>
    <p><action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">With that he got up, pulled on his jacket, opened the lower door, and crept outside.</action></p>
    <p>The moon was shining brightly, and the white pebbles were glistening like silver coins.
        <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">Hansel bent over and filled his jacket pockets with them, as many as would fit.</action></p>
    <p>Then he went back into the house and said, "Don't worry, Gretel. Sleep well." Then he went
        back to bed, and fell asleep.</p>
    <p><action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">The next morning the mother came and woke them both</action> before sunrise, "Get up, you children. We
        are going into the woods. Here is a little piece of bread. Take care and save it until
        midday."</p>
    <p><action agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="eager">Gretel put the bread under her apron, because Hansel's pockets were full of stones,</action> and <action agency="active" gender="male | female" willingness="eager">they
        set forth into the woods.</action></p>
    <p><action agency="active" gender="male | female" willingness="eager">After they had walked a little way,</action> Hansel began stopping again and again and looking back
        toward the house.</p>
    <p>The father said, "Hansel, why are you stopping and looking back? Pay attention now, and keep
        up with us."</p>
    <p>"Oh, father, I am looking at my white cat that is sitting on the roof and wants to say
        good-bye to me."</p>
    <p>The mother said, <description type="negative" gender="male">"You fool,</description> that isn't your cat. That's the morning sun shining on the
        chimney."</p>
    <p>However, <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">Hansel had not been looking at his cat but instead had been dropping the shiny
        pebbles from his pocket onto the path.</action></p>
    <p>When they arrived in the middle of the woods, the father said, "You children gather some
        wood, and I will make a fire so we won't freeze."</p>
    <p><action agency="active" gender="male | female" willingness="eager">Hansel and Gretel gathered together some twigs,</action> a pile as high as a small mountain</p>
    <p>They set it afire, and when the flames were burning well, the mother said, "Lie down by the
        fire and sleep. We will go into the woods to cut down trees. Wait until we come back and get
        you."</p>
    <p><action agency="passive" gender="male | female" willingness="neutral">Hansel and Gretel sat by the fire until midday, and then ate their bread.</action></p>
    <p>They sat on until evening, but the mother and father did not return, and no one came to get
        them.</p>
    <p>When it became dark, <action agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="neutral">Gretel began to cry,</action> but Hansel said, "Wait a little until the moon
        comes up."</p>
    <p>After the moon had come up, <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">he took Gretel by the hand.</action></p>
    <p>The pebbles were lying there like newly minted coins. Glistening, they showed them the
        way.</p>
    <p><action agency="active" gender="male | female" willingness="eager">They walked throughout the entire night, and as morning was breaking, they arrived at the
        father's house.</action></p>
    <p><descriptor type="positive" gender="male">The father was overjoyed when he saw his children once more, for he had not wanted to leave
        them alone.</descriptor> <descriptor type="negative" gender="female">The mother pretended that she too was happy, but secretly she was angry.</descriptor></p>
    <p>Not long afterward there was once again no bread in the house, and one evening Hansel and
        Gretel heard the mother say to the father, "The children found their way back once, and I
        let it be, but again we have only a half loaf of bread in the house. Tomorrow you must take
        them deeper into the woods, so they cannot find their way home. Otherwise there will be no
        help for us."</p>
    <p><action agency="passive" gender="male" willingness="neutral">The man was very disheartened, and he thought it would be better to share the last bit with
        the children, but because he had done it once, he could not say no.</action></p>
    <p>Hansel and Gretel heard the parents' conversation.</p>
    <p><action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">Hansel got up and wanted to gather pebbles once again,</action> but when he came to the door, he found
        that <action agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="neutral">the mother had locked it.</action></p>
    <p>Still, he comforted Gretel and said, "Just go to sleep, Gretel dear. God will help us."</p>
    <p>Early the next morning they received their little pieces of bread, even less than the last
        time.</p>
    <p>On the way, <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">Hansel crumbled his piece in his pocket, then often stood still, and threw crumbs
        onto the ground.</action></p>
    <p>"Why are you always stopping and looking around?" said his father. "Keep walking straight
        ahead."</p>
    <p>"Oh!, I can see my pigeon sitting on the roof. It wants to say good-bye to me."</p>
    <p><descriptor type="negative" gender="male">"You fool,"</descriptor> said his mother, "that isn't your pigeon. That's the morning sun shining on the
        chimney."</p>
    <p><action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">But Hansel crumbled all of his bread and dropped the crumbs onto the path.</action></p>
    <p><action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">The mother took them deeper into the woods than they had ever been in their whole
        lifetime.</action></p>
    <p>There they were told to sleep by a large fire, and that the parents would come and get them
        in the evening.</p>
    <p><action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">At midday Gretel shared her bread with Hansel, because he had scattered all of his along the
        path.</action></p>
    <p>Midday passed, and evening passed, but no one came to get the poor children.</p>
    <p>Hansel comforted Gretel and said, "Wait, when the moon comes up I will be able to see the
        crumbs of bread that I scattered, and they will show us the way back home."</p>
    <p>The moon came up, but when <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">Hansel looked for the crumbs, they were gone.</action> The many thousands
        of birds in the woods had found them and pecked them up.</p>
    <p><action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">Hansel thought that he would still be able to find the way home,</action> and <action agency="active" gender="male | female" willingness="eager">he and Gretel set forth,
        but they soon became totally lost in the great wilderness.</action></p>
    <p><action agency="active" gender="male | female" willingness="eager">They walked through the night and the entire next day, and then, exhausted, they fell asleep.
        They walked another day, but they could not find their way out of the woods.</action></p>
    <p>They were terribly hungry, for they had eaten only a few small berries that were growing on
        the ground.</p>
    <p>On the third day <action agency="active" gender="male | female" willingness="eager">they walked until midday when they came to a little house</action> built entirely
        from bread with a roof made of cake, and the windows were made of clear sugar.</p>
    <p>"Let's sit down and eat our fill," said Hansel. "I'll eat from the roof, and Gretel, you eat
        from the window. That will be nice and sweet for you."</p>
    <p><action agency="passive" gender="male | female" willingness="neutral">Hansel had already eaten a piece from the roof and Gretel had eaten a few round windowpanes,
        and she had just broken out another one when she heard a gentle voice calling out from
        inside:</action></p>
    <p/>
    <p>Nibble, nibble, little mouse,</p>
    <p>Who is nibbling at my house?</p>
    <p>Hansel and Gretel were so frightened that they dropped what they were holding in their hands,
        and immediately they saw a <description type="negative" gender="female">little woman, as old as the hills,</description> creeping out the door.</p>
    <p>She shook her head and said, "Oh, you dear children, where did you come from? Come inside
        with me, and you will be just fine."</p>
    <p><action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">She took them by the hand and led them into her house.</action></p>
    <p>Then <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">she served them a good meal:</action> pancakes with sugar, apples, and nuts; and made two nice
        beds for them.</p>
    <p><action agency="passive" gender="male | female" willingness="neutral">Hansel and Gretel went to bed, thinking it was though they were in heaven.</action></p>
    <p>But the <description type="negative" gender="female">old woman was a wicked witch who was lying in wait there for children.</description></p>
    <p><action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">She had built her house of bread in order to lure them to her, and if she captured one, she
        would kill him, cook him, and eat him; and for her that was a day to celebrate.</action></p>
    <p>So she was overjoyed that Hansel and Gretel had found their way to her.</p>
    <p>Early the next morning, before they awoke, <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">she got up, went to their beds, and looked at the
        two of them lying there</action> so peacefully.</p>
    <p>"They will be a good mouthful," she thought.</p>
    <p><action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">She grabbed Hansel and put him in a little stall,</action> and when he awoke, he found himself in a
        cage, locked up like a young dog, and he could walk only a few steps.</p>
    <p>Then <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">she shook Gretel and cried,</action> "Get up, <description type="negative" gender="female">lazybones!</description> Fetch water. Go into the kitchen and
        cook something to eat. Your brother is locked in that stall there. I want to fatten him up,
        and <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">when he is fat I am going to eat him.</action> For now, you have to feed him."</p>
    <p><action agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="hesitant">Gretel was frightened and cried, but she had to do what the witch demanded.</action></p>
    <p>Now Hansel was given the best things to eat every day, so he would get fat, but Gretel
        received nothing but crayfish shells.</p>
    <p>Every day the <description type="negative" gender="female">old woman</description> came and said, "Hansel, stick out your finger, so I can feel if you
        are fat enough yet."</p>
    <p>But <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">Hansel always stuck out a little bone,</action> and she wondered why he didn't get any fatter.</p>
    <p>After four weeks, one evening she said to Gretel, "Hurry up and fetch some water. Whether
        your brother is fat enough now or not, tomorrow <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">I am going to slaughter him and boil him.</action> In
        the meantime I want to start the dough that we will bake to go with him."</p>
    <p><action agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="hesitant">With a sad heart Gretel fetched the water in which Hansel was to be boiled.</action></p>
    <p>The next morning Gretel had to get up early, make a fire, and hang up the kettle with
        water.</p>
    <p>"Watch it until it boils," said the witch. "I am going to make a fire in the oven and put the
        bread into it."</p>
    <p><action agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="neutral">Gretel stood in the kitchen and cried tears of blood and thought that it would have been
        better if wild animals had devoured them in the woods,</action> for then they would at least have
        died together and would not now be suffering so, and she herself would not have to be
        boiling the water that would kill her dear brother; and she prayed, "Dear God, save us poor
        children."</p>
    <p>Then the <description type="negative" gender="female">old woman</description> called, "Gretel, come here right now to the oven."</p>
    <p>And when Gretel came, she said, "Look inside and see if the bread is nicely brown and done,
        for my eyes are weak, and I can't see that far. If you can't see that far either, then sit
        on the board, and I'll push you inside, then you can walk around inside and take a
        look."</p>
    <p>But once Gretel was inside, the <description type="negative" gender="female">witch</description> intended to close the door, and bake her in the hot
        oven, and eat her as well. That is what the wicked witch was thinking, and that is why she
        called Gretel.</p>
    <p>However, God let <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">Gretel know this, so she said, "I don't know how to do that. First show me.
        You sit on the board, and I will push you inside."</action></p>
    <p>So the old woman sat on the board, and since she was light, <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">Gretel pushed her all the way
        inside, then quickly closed the door and secured it with an iron bar.</action></p>
    <p>The <description type="negative" gender="female">old woman</description> in the hot oven began to cry and to wail, but Gretel ran away, and the <description type="negative" gender="female">old
        woman</description> burned up miserably.</p>
    <p><action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">Gretel ran to Hansel and unlocked his door.</action></p>
    <p><action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">He jumped out,</action> and they kissed each other and were overjoyed.</p>
    <p>The whole house was filled with precious stones and pearls.</p>
    <p><action agency="active" gender="male | female" willingness="eager">They filled their pockets, then ran away and found their way back home.</action></p>
    <p>The <description type="positive" gender="male">father rejoiced when he saw them once more, for he had not had a happy day since they had
        been gone,</description> and now he was a <description type="positive" gender="male">rich man.</description> However, the mother had died.</p>
    <empty happy_ending="true"></empty>
    <source>The Grimms' specific source is unclear. Although they state that it derives "from
        various stories from Hessen," a handwritten marginal note in the Grimms' personal copy of
        the first edition reveals that in 1813 Henriette Dorothea (Dortchen) Wild contributed the
        children's verse answer to the witch, "The wind, the wind,/ The heavenly child," which
        rhymes in German: "Der Wind, der Wind,/ Das himmlische Kind." It is likely that the Grimms
        heard the entire story in the Wild household. Wilhelm Grimm married Dortchen Wild in
        1825.</source>
    <year>First edition, 1812</year>
    <translator>Translated by D. L. Ashliman. © 2000-2002.</translator>
</story>
