<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fairytale>
    <title>Little Red Cap</title>

    <auhtor>Jacob and Wilhelm Grimm</auhtor>

    <p>Once upon a time there was a <descriptor type="positive" gender="female">sweet</descriptor>
        <descriptor type="neutral" gender="female">little</descriptor> girl. Everyone who saw her
        liked her, but most of all her grandmother, who did not know what to give the child next.
        Once she <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">gave her a little cap
            made of red velvet</action>. Because it suited her so well, and she wanted to wear it
        all the time, she <action agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="neutral">came to be
            known as Little Red Cap</action>.</p>
    <p>One day her mother said to her, "Come Little Red Cap. Here is a piece of cake and a bottle of
        wine. Take them to your grandmother. She is <descriptor type="negative" gender="female"
            >sick</descriptor> and <descriptor type="negative" gender="female">weak</descriptor>,
        and they will do her well. Mind your manners and give her my greetings. Behave yourself on
        the way, and do not leave the path, or you might fall down and break the glass, and then
        there will be nothing for your <descriptor type="negative" gender="female">sick</descriptor>
        grandmother."</p>

    <p>Little Red Cap <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">promised to obey
            her mother</action>. The grandmother lived out in the woods, a half hour from the
        village. When Little Red Cap entered the woods a wolf came up to her. <action
            agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="neutral">She did not know what a
                <descriptor type="negative" gender="male">wicked</descriptor> animal he was, and was
            not afraid of him</action>.</p>

    <p>"Good day to you, Little Red Cap."</p>

    <p>"Thank you, wolf."</p>

    <p>"Where are you going so early, Little Red Cap?"</p>

    <p>"To grandmother's."</p>

    <p>"And what are you carrying under your apron?"</p>

    <p>"Grandmother is <descriptor type="negative" gender="female">sick</descriptor> and <descriptor
            type="negative" gender="female">weak</descriptor>, and I <action agency="active"
            gender="female" willingness="eager">am taking her some cake and wine</action>. We baked
        yesterday, and they should give her strength."</p>

    <p>"Little Red Cap, just where does your grandmother live?"</p>

    <p>"Her house is a good quarter hour from here in the woods, under the three large oak trees.
        There's a hedge of hazel bushes there. You must know the place," said Little Red Cap.</p>

    <p>The wolf thought to himself, "Now there is a tasty bite for me. Just how are you going to
        catch her?" Then he said, "Listen, Little Red Cap, haven't you seen the beautiful flowers
        that are blossoming in the woods? Why don't you go and take a look? And I don't believe you
        can hear how beautifully the birds are singing. You are walking along as though you were on
        your way to school in the village. It is very beautiful in the woods."</p>

    <p>Little Red Cap <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">opened her eyes
            and saw the sunlight breaking through the trees and how the ground was covered with
            beautiful flowers. She thought, "If a take a bouquet to grandmother, she will be very
            pleased. Anyway, it is still early, and I'll be home on time." And she ran off into the
            woods looking for flowers. Each time she picked one she thought that she could see an
            even more beautiful one a little way off, and she ran after it, going further and
            further into the woods</action>. But the wolf <action agency="active" gender="male"
            willingness="eager">ran straight to the grandmother's house and knocked on the
            door</action>.</p>

    <p>"Who's there?"</p>

    <p>"Little Red Cap. I'm <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">bringing you
            some cake and wine</action>. Open the door for me."</p>

    <p>"Just press the latch," called out the grandmother. "I'm too <descriptor type="negative"
            gender="female">weak</descriptor> to get up."</p>

    <p>The wolf <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">pressed the latch, and the
            door opened. He stepped inside, went straight to the grandmother's bed, and ate her up.
            Then he took her clothes, put them on, and put her cap on his head. He got into her bed
            and pulled the curtains shut</action>.</p>

    <p>Little Red Cap <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">had run after
            flowers, and did not continue on her way to grandmother's until she had gathered all
            that she could carry. When she arrived, she found, to her surprise, that the door was
            open</action>. She <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="hesitant">walked
            into the parlor, and everything looked so strange that she thought, "Oh, my God, why am
            I so afraid? I usually like it at grandmother's."</action> Then she <action
            agency="active" gender="female" willingness="hesitant">went to the bed and pulled back
            the curtains</action>. Grandmother <action agency="passive" gender="female"
            willingness="neutral">was lying there with her cap pulled down over her face and
                <descriptor type="negative" gender="female">looking very
            strange</descriptor></action>.</p>

    <p>"Oh, grandmother, <descriptor type="neutral" gender="male">what big ears you
            have</descriptor>!"</p>

    <p>"All the better to hear you with."</p>

    <p>"Oh, grandmother, <descriptor type="neutral" gender="male">what big eyes you
            have</descriptor>!"</p>

    <p>"All the better to see you with."</p>

    <p>"Oh, grandmother, <descriptor type="neutral" gender="male">what big hands you
            have</descriptor>!"</p>

    <p>"All the better to grab you with!"</p>

    <p>"Oh, grandmother, <descriptor type="negative" gender="male">what a horribly big mouth you
            have</descriptor>!"</p>

    <p>"All the better to eat you with!" And with that he <action agency="active" gender="male"
            willingness="eager">jumped out of bed, jumped on top of <descriptor type="negative"
                gender="female">poor</descriptor> Little Red Cap, and ate her up. As soon as the
            wolf had finished this tasty bite, he climbed back into bed, fell asleep, and began to
            snore very loudly</action>.</p>

    <p>A huntsman was just passing by. He thought it strange that the <descriptor type="neutral"
            gender="female">old</descriptor> woman was <action agency="passive" gender="female"
            willingness="neutral">snoring so loudly</action>, so he <action agency="active"
            gender="male" willingness="eager">decided to take a look. He stepped inside, and in the
            bed there lay the wolf that he had been hunting for such a long time</action>. "He has
        eaten the grandmother, but perhaps she still can be saved. I won't shoot him," thought the
        huntsman. So he <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">took a pair of
            scissors and cut open his belly</action>.</p>

    <p>He had cut only a few strokes when he saw the red cap shining through. He cut a little more,
        and the girl <action agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="eager">jumped out and
            cried, "Oh, I was so frightened! It was so dark inside the wolf's body!"</action></p>

    <p>And then the grandmother <action agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="neutral">came
            out alive as well</action>. Then Little Red Cap <action agency="active" gender="female"
            willingness="eager">fetched some large heavy stones</action>. They filled the wolf's
        body with them, and <action agency="passive" gender="male" willingness="neutral">when he
            woke up and tried to run away, the stones were so heavy that he fell down
        dead</action>.</p>

    <p>The three of them were happy. The huntsman <action agency="active" gender="male"
            willingness="eager">took the wolf's pelt</action>. The grandmother <action
            agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">ate the cake and drank the wine that
            Little Red Cap had brought</action>. And Little Red Cap thought to herself, "<action
            agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">As long as I live, I will never
            leave the path and run off into the woods by myself if mother tells me not
        to</action>."</p>

    <p>They also tell how Little Red Cap <action agency="passive" gender="female"
            willingness="eager">was taking some baked things to her grandmother another time, when
            another wolf <action agency="passive" gender="male" willingness="eager">spoke to her and
                wanted her to leave the path</action></action>. But Little Red Cap <action
            agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">took care and went straight to
            grandmother's</action>. She told her that she had seen the wolf, and that he had wished
        her a good day, but had stared at her in a <descriptor type="negative" gender="male"
            >wicked</descriptor> manner. "If we hadn't been on a public road, he <action
            agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="neutral">would have eaten me up</action>,"
        she said.</p>

    <p>"Come," said the grandmother. "<action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager"
            >Let's lock the door, so he can't get in</action>."</p>

    <p>Soon afterward the wolf <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">knocked on
            the door and called out, "Open up, grandmother. It's Little Red Cap, and I'm bringing
            you some baked things."</action></p>

    <p>They remained silent, and did not open the door. The <descriptor type="negative"
            gender="male">wicked</descriptor> one <action agency="active" gender="male"
            willingness="eager">walked around the house several times, and finally jumped onto the
            roof. He wanted to wait until Little Red Cap went home that evening, then follow her and
            eat her up in the darkness</action>. But the grandmother saw what he was up to. There
        was a large stone trough in front of the house.</p>

    <p>"Fetch a bucket, Little Red Cap," she said. "Yesterday I cooked some sausage. Carry the water
        that I boiled them with to the trough." Little Red Cap <action agency="active"
            gender="female" willingness="eager">carried water until the large, large trough was
            clear full</action>. <action agency="passive" gender="male" willingness="eager">The
            smell of sausage arose into the wolf's nose. He sniffed and looked down, stretching his
            neck so long that he could no longer hold himself, and he began to slide. He slid off
            the roof, fell into the trough, and drowned</action>. And Little Red Cap <action
            agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">returned home happily and
            safely</action>.</p>
    <empty happy_ending="true"/>
    <metadata>
        <source>Source: "Rothkäppchen," Kinder- und Hausmärchen, 1st ed. (Berlin:
            Realschulbuchhandlung, 1812), v. 1, no. 26, pp. 113-18.</source>
        <translator>Translated by D. L. Ashliman.</translator> The <source>Grimms' source for the
            first variant (the main story) was Jeanette Hassenpflug (1791-1860). Marie Hassenpflug
            (1788-1856) provided them with the second variant (the concluding episode, introduced
            with the sentence "They also tell how Little Red Cap was taking some baked things to her
            grandmother another time...."</source>
        <note>The German title of this tale is Rotkäppchen (Rothkäppchen in the nineteenth-century
            spelling of the Grimm brothers).</note>
        <note>Link to an English translation of the Grimms' final version (edition of 1857) of
            Little Red Cap.</note>
        <note>Link to the German text of the Grimms' final version: "Rothkäppchen," Kinder- und
            Hausmärchen, gesammelt durch die Brüder Grimm, 7th edition, vol. 1 (Göttingen: Verlag
            der Dieterichschen Buchhandlung, 1857), no. 26, pp. 140-44.</note>
        <note>Link to the Grimm Brothers Home Page.</note>
        <note>Return to the table of contents.</note>
    </metadata>
</fairytale>
