<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../Downloads/grimm_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<fairytale>
    <metadata>
        <title>Little Red Cap</title>
        <author>Jacob and Wilhelm Grimm</author>
        <source>Source: "Rotkäppchen," Kinder- und Hausmärchen, gesammelt durch die Brüder Grimm,
            vol. 1 (Göttingen: Verlag der Dieterichschen Buchhandlung, <year>1857</year>), no. 26,
            pp. 140-44.</source>
        <translator>Translated by D. L. Ashliman. © 2000-2002.</translator>
    </metadata>

    <body>
        <p>Once upon a time there was a <descriptor type="positive" gender="female"
                >sweet</descriptor>
            <descriptor type="neutral" gender="female">little</descriptor> girl. Everyone who saw
            her liked her, but most of all her grandmother, who did not know what to give the child
            next. Once she <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">gave her a
                little cap made of red velvet</action>. Because it suited her so well, and she
            wanted to wear it all the time, she <action agency="passive" gender="female"
                willingness="neutral">came to be known as Little Red Cap</action>.</p>

        <p>One day her mother said to her, "Come Little Red Cap. Here is a piece of cake and a
            bottle of wine. Take them to your grandmother. She is <descriptor type="negative"
                gender="female">sick</descriptor> and <descriptor type="negative" gender="female"
                >weak</descriptor>, and they will do her well. Mind your manners and give her my
            greetings. Behave yourself on the way, and do not leave the path, or you might fall down
            and break the glass, and then there will be nothing for your grandmother. And when you
            enter her parlor, don't forget to say 'Good morning,' and don't peer into all the
            corners first."</p>

        <p><action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">"I'll do everything just
                right," said Little Red Cap, shaking her mother's hand</action>.</p>

        <p>The grandmother lived out in the woods, a half hour from the village. When Little Red Cap
            entered the woods a wolf came up to her. <action agency="passive" gender="female"
                willingness="neutral">She did not know what a <descriptor type="negative"
                    gender="male">wicked</descriptor> animal he was, and was not afraid of
                him</action>.</p>

        <p>"Good day to you, Little Red Cap."</p>

        <p>"Thank you, wolf."</p>

        <p>"Where are you going so early, Little Red Cap?"</p>

        <p>"To grandmother's."</p>

        <p>"And what are you carrying under your apron?"</p>

        <p>"Grandmother is <descriptor type="negative" gender="female">sick</descriptor> and
                <descriptor type="negative" gender="female">weak</descriptor>, and I <action
                agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">am taking her some cake and
                wine</action>. We baked yesterday, and they should be good for her and give her
            strength."</p>

        <p>"Little Red Cap, just where does your grandmother live?"</p>

        <p>"Her house is good quarter hour from here in the woods, under the three large oak trees.
            There's a hedge of hazel bushes there. You must know the place," said Little Red
            Cap.</p>

        <p>The wolf thought to himself, "Now that <descriptor type="positive" gender="female"
                >sweet</descriptor> young thing is a tasty bite for me. She will taste even better
            than the old woman. You must <descriptor type="negative" gender="male">be
                sly</descriptor>, and you can catch them both."</p>

        <p>He <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">walked along a little while
                with Little Red Cap, then he said, "Little Red Cap, just look at the beautiful
                flowers that are all around us. Why don't you go and take a look? And I don't
                believe you can hear how beautifully the birds are singing. You are walking along as
                though you were on your way to school. It is very beautiful in the
            woods."</action></p>

        <p>Little Red Cap <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">opened her
                eyes and when she saw the sunbeams dancing to and fro through the trees and how the
                ground was covered with beautiful flowers, she thought, "If a take a fresh bouquet
                to grandmother, she will be very pleased. Anyway, it is still early, and I'll be
                home on time." And she ran off the path into the woods looking for flowers. Each
                time she picked one she thought that she could see an even more beautiful one a
                little way off, and she ran after it, going further and further into the
                woods</action>. But the wolf <action agency="active" gender="male"
                willingness="eager">ran straight to the grandmother's house and knocked on the
                door</action>.</p>

        <p>"Who's there?"</p>

        <p>"Little Red Cap. I'm <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">bringing
                you some cake and wine</action>. Open the door."</p>

        <p>"Just press the latch," called out the grandmother. "I'm <descriptor type="negative"
                gender="female">too weak</descriptor> to get up."</p>

        <p>The wolf <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">pressed the latch, and
                the door opened. He stepped inside, went straight to the grandmother's bed, and ate
                her up. Then he put on her clothes, put her cap on his head, got into her bed, and
                pulled the curtains shut</action>.</p>

        <p>Little Red Cap <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="neutral">had run
                after the flowers. After she had gathered so many that she could not carry any more,
                she remembered her grandmother, and then continued on her way to her house</action>.
            She found, to her surprise, that the door was open. She <action agency="active"
                gender="female" willingness="hesitant">walked into the parlor, and everything looked
                so strange that she thought, "Oh, my God, why am I so afraid? I usually like it at
                grandmother's."</action></p>

        <p>She <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="neutral">called out, "Good
                morning!"</action> but <action agency="passive" gender="female"
                willingness="neutral">received no answer</action>.</p>

        <p>Then <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="hesitant">she went to the bed
                and pulled back the curtains</action>. Grandmother <action agency="passive"
                gender="female" willingness="neutral">was lying there with her cap pulled down over
                her face and <descriptor type="negative" gender="female">looking very
                    strange</descriptor>.</action></p>

        <p>"Oh, grandmother, <descriptor type="neutral" gender="male">what big ears you
                have</descriptor>!"</p>

        <p>"All the better to hear you with."</p>

        <p>"Oh, grandmother, <descriptor type="neutral" gender="male">what big eyes you
                have</descriptor>!"</p>

        <p>"All the better to see you with."</p>

        <p>"Oh, grandmother, <descriptor type="neutral" gender="male">what big hands you
                have</descriptor>!"</p>

        <p>"All the better to grab you with!"</p>

        <p>"Oh, grandmother, <descriptor type="negative" gender="male">what a horribly big mouth you
                have</descriptor>!"</p>

        <p>"All the better to eat you with!"</p>

        <p>The wolf had scarcely finished speaking when he <action agency="active" gender="male"
                willingness="eager">jumped from the bed with a single leap and ate up <descriptor
                    type="negative" gender="female">poor</descriptor> Little Red Cap. As soon as the
                wolf had satisfied his desires, he climbed back into bed, fell asleep, and began to
                snore very loudly</action>.</p>

        <p>A huntsman was just passing by. He thought, "The <descriptor type="neutral"
                gender="female">old</descriptor> woman is <action agency="passive" gender="female"
                willingness="neutral">snoring so loudly</action>. You <action agency="passive"
                gender="male" willingness="eager">had better see if something is wrong with
                her</action>."</p>

        <p>He <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">stepped into the parlor, and
                when he approached the bed, he saw the wolf lying there. "So here I find you, you
                    <descriptor type="neutral" gender="male">old</descriptor>
                <descriptor type="negative" gender="male">sinner</descriptor>," he said.</action> "I
                <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">have been hunting for you
                a long time</action>."</p>

        <p>He <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">was about to aim his rifle
                when it occurred to him that the wolf might have eaten the grandmother, and that she
                still might be rescued. So instead of shooting, he took a pair of scissors and began
                to cut open the wolf's belly</action>. After a few cuts he saw the red cap shining
            through., and after a few more cuts the girl <action agency="passive" gender="female"
                willingness="eager">jumped out, crying, "Oh, I was so frightened! It was so dark
                inside the wolf's body!"</action></p>

        <p>And then the grandmother <action agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="neutral"
                >came out as well, alive but hardly able to breathe</action>. Then Little Red Cap
                <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">fetched some large
                stones. She filled the wolf's body with them</action>, and <action agency="passive"
                gender="male" willingness="neutral">when he woke up and tried to run away, the
                stones were so heavy that he immediately fell down dead</action>.</p>

        <p>The three of them were happy. The huntsman <action agency="active" gender="male"
                willingness="eager">skinned the wolf and went home with the pelt</action>. The
            grandmother <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">ate the cake and
                drank the wine that Little Red Cap had brought</action>. And Little Red Cap thought,
                "<action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">As long as I live, I
                will never leave the path and run off into the woods by myself if mother tells me
                not to</action>."</p>

        <p>They also tell how Little Red Cap <action agency="passive" gender="female"
                willingness="eager">was taking some baked things to her grandmother another time,
                when another wolf <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">spoke to
                    her and wanted her to leave the path</action></action>. But Little Red Cap
                <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">took care and went
                straight to grandmother's</action>. She told her that she had seen the wolf, and
            that he had wished her a good day, but had stared at her in a wicked manner. "If we
            hadn't been on a public road, he <action agency="passive" gender="female"
                willingness="neutral">would have eaten me up</action>," she said.</p>

        <p>"Come," said the grandmother. "<action agency="active" gender="female"
                willingness="eager">Let's lock the door, so he can't get in</action>."</p>

        <p>Soon afterward the wolf <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">knocked
                on the door and called out, "Open up, grandmother. It's Little Red Cap, and I'm
                bringing you some baked things."</action></p>

        <p>They <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">remained silent, and did
                not open the door</action>. Gray-Head <action agency="active" gender="male"
                willingness="eager">crept around the house several times, and finally jumped onto
                the roof. He wanted to wait until Little Red Cap went home that evening, then follow
                her and eat her up in the darkness</action>. But the grandmother saw what he was up
            to. There was a large stone trough in front of the house.</p>

        <p>"Fetch a bucket, Little Red Cap," she said to the child. "Yesterday I cooked some
            sausage. Carry the water that I boiled them with to the trough." Little Red Cap <action
                agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">carried water until the large,
                large trough was clear full</action>. The smell of sausage arose into the wolf's
            nose. He <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">sniffed and looked
                down, stretching his neck so long that he could no longer hold himself, and he began
                to slide.</action> He <action agency="passive" gender="male" willingness="neutral"
                >slid off the roof, fell into the trough, and drowned</action>. And Little Red Cap
                <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">returned home
                happily</action>, and no one harmed her.</p>
        <empty happy_ending="true"/>
    </body>
</fairytale>
