<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../grimm_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<fairytale>
    <metadata Translator="D.L. Ashliman" Year="1812" Source="https://sites.pitt.edu/~dash/grimm012a.html" Storynumber="12"/>
    <title>Rapunzel</title>
    <author>Jacob and Wilhelm Grimm</author>
    <body>
    <p>Once upon a time there was a man and a woman who had long wished for a child but had never
        received one.</p>
    <p>Finally, however, <action agency="active" gender="male | female" willingness="eager">the woman came to be with child.</action></p>
    <p>Through the small rear window of these people's house they could see into a <descriptor type="positive" gender="female">fairy's</descriptor> garden
        that was filled with flowers and herbs of all kinds.</p>
    <p>No one dared enter this garden.</p>
    <p>One day the woman was standing at this window, and she saw the most beautiful rapunzel in a
        bed.</p>
    <p><action agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="hesitant">She longed for some, but not knowing how to get any, she became miserably ill.</action></p>
    <p>Her husband was frightened, and asked her why she was doing so poorly.</p>
    <p>"Oh, if I do not get some rapunzel from the garden behind our house, I shall surely die," she
        said.</p>
    <p>The man, who loved her dearly, <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">decided to get her some, whatever the cost.</action></p>
    <p><action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">One evening he climbed over the high wall, hastily dug up a handful of rapunzel, and took it
        to his wife.</action></p>
    <p>She immediately made a salad from it, which she devoured greedily.</p>
    <p>It tasted so very good to her that by the next day her desire for more had grown
        threefold.</p>
    <p><action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">The man saw that there would be no peace, so once again he climbed into the garden.</action></p>
    <p>To his horror, the <descriptor type="positive" gender="female">fairy</descriptor> was standing there.</p>
    <p><action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">She scolded him fiercely</action> for daring to enter and steal from her garden.</p>
    <p><action agency="passive" gender="male" willingness="eager">He excused himself as best he could with his wife's pregnancy, and how it would be dangerous
        to deny her anything.</action></p>
    <p>Finally the <descriptor type="positive" gender="female">fairy</descriptor> spoke, "I will accept your excuse and even allow you to take as much
        rapunzel as you want, if you will <descriptor type="negative" gender="female">give me the child that your wife is now carrying."</descriptor></p>
    <p><action agency="passive" gender="male" willingness="neutral">In his fear the man agreed to everything.</action></p>
    <p>When the woman gave birth, the <descriptor type="positive" gender="female">fairy</descriptor> appeared, named the little girl Rapunzel, and <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">took her
        away.</action></p>
    <p>This Rapunzel became the most <descriptor type="positive" gender="female">beautiful child</descriptor> under the sun, but when she was twelve years
        old, the <descriptor type="positive" gender="female">fairy</descriptor> <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">locked her in a high tower that had neither a door nor a stairway, but only a
        tiny little window at the very top.</action></p>
    <p>When the <descriptor type="positive" gender="female">fairy</descriptor> wanted to enter, <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">she stood below and called out:</action></p>
    <p>Rapunzel, Rapunzel!</p>
    <p>Let down your hair to me.</p>
    <p><descriptor type="positive" gender="female">Rapunzel had splendid hair, as fine as spun gold.</descriptor></p>
    <p>When the <descriptor type="positive" gender="female">fairy</descriptor> called out, <action agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="neutral">she untied it, wound it around a window hook, let it fall twenty
        yards to the ground,</action> and the <descriptor type="positive" gender="female">fairy</descriptor> <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">climbed up it.</action></p>
    <p>One day a young prince came through the forest where the tower stood.</p>
    <p>He saw the <descriptor type="positive" gender="female">beautiful Rapunzel</descriptor> standing at her window, heard her sing with her <descriptor type="positive" gender="female">sweet voice,</descriptor>
        and <action agency="passive" gender="male" willingness="eager">fell in love with her.</action></p>
    <p>Because there was no door in the tower and no ladder was tall enough to reach her, <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">He came to
        the forest every day,</action> until once he saw the <descriptor type="positive" gender="female">fairy,</descriptor> who said:</p>
    <p>Rapunzel, Rapunzel!</p>
    <p>Let down your hair.</p>
    <p>Then he knew which ladder would get him into the tower.</p>
    <p><action agency="passive" gender="male" willingness="eager">He remembered the words that he would have to speak, and the next day, as soon as it was
        dark, he went to the tower and called upward:</action></p>
    <p>Rapunzel, Rapunzel!</p>
    <p>Let down your hair!</p>
    <p><action agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="eager">She let her hair fall.</action> <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">He tied himself to it and was pulled up.</action></p>
    <p>At first Rapunzel was frightened, but soon she came to like the young king so well that <action agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="eager">she
        arranged for him to come every day and be pulled up.</action> Thus they lived in joy and pleasure for
        a long time.</p>
    <p>The <descriptor type="positive" gender="female">fairy</descriptor> did not discover what was happening until one day Rapunzel said to her, "Frau
        Gothel, tell me why it is that my clothes are all too tight. They no longer fit me."</p>
    <p><descriptor type="negative" gender="female">"You godless child,"</descriptor> said the <descriptor type="positive" gender="female">fairy.</descriptor> "What am I hearing from you?" She immediately saw how
        <descriptor type="negative" gender="female">she had been deceived and was terribly angry.</descriptor></p>
    <p>She took <descriptor type="positive" gender="female">Rapunzel's beautiful hair,</descriptor> <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">wrapped it a few times around her left hand, grasped a
        pair of scissors with her right hand, and snip snip, cut it off.</action></p>
    <p>Then <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">she sent Rapunzel into a wilderness</action> where <action agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="neutral">she suffered greatly and where, after a time,
        she gave birth to twins, a boy and a girl.</action></p>
    <p>On the evening of the same day that she sent Rapunzel away, the <descriptor type="positive" gender="female">fairy</descriptor> <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">tied the cut-off hair
        to the hook at the top of the tower,</action> and when the prince called out:</p>
    <p>Rapunzel, Rapunzel!</p>
    <p>Let down your hair!</p>
    <p>she let down the hair.</p>
    <p>The prince was startled to find the <descriptor type="positive" gender="female">fairy</descriptor> instead of his <descriptor type="positive" gender="female">beloved Rapunzel.</descriptor></p>
    <p>"Do you know what, <descriptor type="negative" gender="female">evil</descriptor> one?" cried the <descriptor type="negative" gender="female">angry fairy</descriptor>. "You have lost Rapunzel forever."</p>
    <p><action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">The prince, in his despair, threw himself from the tower.</action></p>
    <p>He escaped with his life, but he lost his eyesight in the fall.</p>
    <p><action agency="passive" gender="male" willingness="neutral">Sorrowfully he wandered about in the forest weeping and, eating nothing but grass and
        roots.</action></p>
    <p><action agency="passive" gender="male" willingness="neuttral">Some years later he happened into the wilderness where Rapunzel lived miserably with her
        children.</action></p>
    <p>He thought that her voice was familiar.</p>
    <p>She recognized him instantly as well and <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">threw her arms around his neck.</action></p>
    <p><action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">Two of her tears fell into his eyes, and they became clear once again, and he could see as
        well as before.</action></p>
    <ending happy_ending="true"/>
    </body>
</fairytale>
