<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../Downloads/grimm_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<fairytale>
    <metadata>
        <title>Rumpelstiltskin</title>
        <author>Jacob and Wilhelm Grimm</author>
        <source>Source: Jacob and Wilhelm Grimm, "Rumpelstilzchen," Kinder- und Hausmärchen, vol. 1
            (Göttingen: Verlag der Dieterichschen Buchhandlung, <year>1857</year>) [Children's and
            Household Tales -- Grimms' Fairy Tales], no. 55, pp. 281-84.</source>
        <translator>Translated by D. L. Ashliman. © 2002.</translator>
    </metadata>

    <body>
        <p>Once upon a time there was a <descriptor type="neutral" gender="male">miller</descriptor>
            who was <descriptor type="negative" gender="male">poor</descriptor>, but who had a
                <descriptor type="positive" gender="female">beautiful</descriptor> daughter. Now it
            happened that he <action agency="passive" gender="male" willingness="eager">got into a
                conversation with the king, and to make an impression on him he said, "I have a
                daughter who can spin straw into gold."</action></p>

        <p>The king said to the miller, "That is an art that I really like. If your daughter is as
            skillful as you say, then bring her to my castle tomorrow, and <action agency="active"
                gender="male" willingness="eager">I will put her to the test</action>."</p>

        <p>When the girl <action agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="hesitant">was brought
                to him he led her into a room that was entirely filled with straw. Giving her a
                spinning wheel and a reel, he said, "Get to work now. Spin all night, and if by
                morning you have not spun this straw into gold, then you will have to die."</action>
            Then <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">he himself locked the
                room</action>, and she was there all alone.</p>

        <p>The poor miller's daughter sat there, and for her life she did not know what to do. She
            had no idea how to spin straw into gold. <action agency="passive" gender="female"
                willingness="neutral">She became more and more afraid, and finally began to
                cry</action>.</p>

        <p>Then suddenly the door opened. A <descriptor type="neutral" gender="male"
                >little</descriptor> man stepped inside and said, "Good evening, Mistress Miller,
            why are you crying so?"</p>

        <p>"Oh," answered the girl, "I am supposed to spin straw into gold, and I do not know how to
            do it."</p>

        <p>The <descriptor type="neutral" gender="male">little</descriptor> man said, "What will you
            give me if I spin it for you?"</p>

        <p>"My necklace," said the girl.</p>

        <p>The <descriptor type="neutral" gender="male">little</descriptor> man took the necklace,
            sat down before the spinning wheel, and whir, whir, whir, three times pulled, and the
            spool was full. Then he put another one on, and whir, whir, whir, three times pulled,
            and the second one was full as well. So it went until morning, and then all the straw
            was spun, and all the spools were filled with gold.</p>

        <p>At sunrise the king came, and when he saw the gold he was surprised and happy, but his
            heart became even more <descriptor type="negative" gender="male">greedy</descriptor> for
            gold. He had the miller's daughter taken to another room filled with straw. It was even
            larger, and <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">he ordered her to
                spin it in one night</action>, if she valued her life.</p>

        <p>The girl <action agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="neutral">did not know what
                to do, and she cried</action>. Once again the door opened, and the <descriptor
                type="neutral" gender="male">little </descriptor> man appeared. He said, "<action
                agency="passive" gender="male" willingness="eager">What will you give me if I spin
                the straw into gold for you?"</action></p>

        <p><action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="hesitant">"The ring from my finger,"
                answered the girl</action>.</p>

        <p>The <descriptor type="neutral" gender="male">little</descriptor> man <action
                agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">took the ring, and began once
                again to whir with the spinning wheel. By morning he had spun all the straw into
                glistening gold</action>. The king was happy beyond measure when he saw it, but he
            still did not have his fill of gold. He had the miller's daughter taken to a still
            larger room filled with straw, and said, "Tonight you must spin this too. If you succeed
            you shall become my wife." He thought, "Even if she is only a miller's daughter, I will
            not find a richer wife in all the world."</p>

        <p>When the girl was alone the <descriptor type="neutral" gender="male">little</descriptor>
            man returned for a third time. He said, "What will you give me if I spin the straw this
            time?"</p>

        <p>"I have nothing more that I could give you," answered the girl.</p>

        <p>"Then promise me, after you are queen, your first child."</p>

        <p>"Who knows what will happen," thought the miller's daughter, and <action agency="active"
                gender="female" willingness="hesitant">not knowing what else to do, she promised the
                    <descriptor type="neutral" gender="male">little man</descriptor> what he
                demanded</action>. In return the <descriptor type="neutral" gender="male">little
                man</descriptor> once again spun the straw into gold.</p>

        <p>When in the morning the king came and found everything just as he desired, he married
            her, and the <descriptor type="positive" gender="female">beautiful</descriptor>
            <descriptor type="neutral" gender="female">miller's daughter</descriptor>
            <action agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="neutral">became
            queen</action>.</p>

        <p>A year later she brought a <descriptor type="positive" gender="neutral">beautiful
                child</descriptor> to the world. She thought no more about the <descriptor
                type="neutral" gender="male">little man</descriptor>, but suddenly he appeared in
            her room and said, "Now give me that which you promised."</p>

        <p>The queen took fright and offered the little man all the wealth of the kingdom if he
            would let her keep the child, but the <descriptor type="neutral" gender="male">little
                man</descriptor> said, "No. Something living is dearer to me than all the treasures
            of the world."</p>

        <p>Then the queen began lamenting and crying so much that the <descriptor type="neutral"
                gender="male">little man</descriptor> took pity on her and said, "I will give you
            three days' time. If by then you know my name, then you shall keep your child."</p>

        <p>The queen spent the entire night thinking of all the names she had ever heard. Then
                <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">she sent a messenger
                into the country to inquire far and wide what other names there were</action>. When
            the <descriptor type="neutral" gender="male">little man</descriptor> returned the next
            day she began with Kaspar, Melchior, Balzer, and said in order all the names she knew.
            After each one the <descriptor type="neutral" gender="male">little man</descriptor>
            said, "That is not my name."</p>

        <p>The second day <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">she sent
                inquiries into the neighborhood as to what names people had</action>. She recited
            the most unusual and most curious names to the <descriptor type="neutral" gender="male"
                >little man</descriptor>: "Is your name perhaps Beastrib? Or Muttoncalf? Or
            Legstring?"</p>

        <p>But he always answered, "That is not my name."</p>

        <p>On the third day the messenger <action agency="passive" gender="male"
                willingness="neutral">returned and said, "I have not been able to find a single new
                name, but when I was approaching a high mountain in the corner of the woods, there
                where the fox and the hare say good-night, I saw a little house</action>. A fire was
            burning in front of the house, and an altogether <descriptor type="neutral"
                gender="male">comical</descriptor>
            <descriptor type="neutral" gender="male">little man</descriptor> was jumping around the
            fire, hopping on one leg and calling out:</p>

        <lg>
            <l><action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">Today I'll bake; tomorrow
                    I'll brew</action>,</l>
            <l><action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">Then I'll fetch the queen's
                    new child</action>,</l>
            <l>It is good that no one knows,</l>
            <l>Rumpelstiltskin is my name.</l>
        </lg>
        <p>You can imagine how happy the queen was when she heard that name. Soon afterward the
                <descriptor type="neutral" gender="male">little</descriptor> man came in and asked,
            "Now, Madame Queen, what is my name?"</p>

        <p>She first asked, "Is your name Kunz?"</p>

        <p>"No."</p>

        <p>"Is your name Heinz?"</p>

        <p>"No."</p>

        <p>"Is your name perhaps Rumpelstiltskin?"</p>

        <p>"The devil told you that! The devil <action agency="passive" gender="female"
                willingness="eager">told you that</action>!" shouted the <descriptor type="neutral"
                gender="male">little man</descriptor>, and with anger <action agency="active"
                gender="male" willingness="eager">he stomped his right foot so hard into the ground
                that he fell in up to his waist. Then with both hands he took hold of his left foot
                and ripped himself up the middle in two</action>.</p>
        <ending happy_ending="true"/>
    </body>
</fairytale>
