<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../grimm_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<fairytale>
    <metadata>
        <title>Frau Holle (1812)</title>
        <author>Jacob and Wilhelm Grimm</author>
    </metadata>
    <body>
    <p>A widow had two daughters, the one was <descriptor type="positive" gender="female"
            >beautiful</descriptor> and <descriptor type="positive" gender="female"
            >industrious</descriptor>, the other <descriptor type="negative" gender="female"
            >ugly</descriptor> and <descriptor type="negative" gender="female">lazy</descriptor>.
        She greatly <action agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="neutral">favored</action>
        the <descriptor type="negative" gender="female">ugly</descriptor>, <descriptor
            type="negative" gender="female">lazy</descriptor> girl, because she was her own
        daughter. And the other one had to do all the work, and was truly a <descriptor
            type="negative" gender="female">Cinderella</descriptor> in the house.</p>
    <p>Once the girl <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="neutral">went to fetch
            water</action>, and when she leaned over to pull the bucket from the well, she leaned
        over too far and <action agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="hesitant">fell
            in</action>.</p>
    <p>And when she <action agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="neutral">awoke</action>
        and came to herself again, she was in a beautiful meadow. The sun was shining, and there
        were many thousands of flowers. She walked across this meadow and came to an oven full of
        bread. The bread called out, "Oh, take me out. Take me out, or I'll burn. I've been
        thoroughly baked for a long time!" So she <action agency="active" gender="female"
            willingness="neutral">stepped up to it</action> and <action agency="active"
            gender="female" willingness="neutral">took everything out</action>.</p>
    <p>After that she walked further and came to a tree laden with apples. "Shake me! Shake me! We
        apples are all ripe!" cried the tree. So she <action agency="active" gender="female"
            willingness="neutral">shook the tree</action> until the apples fell as though it were
        raining apples. When none were left in the tree, she <action agency="passive"
            gender="female" willingness="neutral">continued on her way</action>.</p>
    <p>Finally she came to a small house. An old woman was peering out from inside. She had very
            <descriptor type="negative" gender="female">large teeth</descriptor>, which <descriptor
            type="negative" gender="female">frightened</descriptor> the girl, and she wanted to run
        away. But the old woman called out to her, "Don't be afraid, dear child. Stay here with me,
        and if you do my housework in an orderly fashion, it will go well with you. Only you must
        take care to make my bed well and shake it diligently until the feathers fly, then it will
        snow in the world. I am Frau Holle."</p>
    <p>Because the old woman spoke so <descriptor type="negative" gender="female"
            >kindly</descriptor> to her, the girl agreed, and started in her service. The girl took
        care of everything to Frau Holle's satisfaction and always <action agency="active"
            gender="female" willingness="eager">shook her featherbed</action> vigorously. Therefore
        she had a good life with her: no angry words, and boiled or roast meat every day.</p>
    <p>Now after she had been with Frau Holle for a time, her heart saddened. Even though she was
        many thousands of times better off here than at home, still she had a <action
            agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="eager">yearning</action> to return.
        Finally she said to the old woman, "I have such a longing for home, and even though I am
        very well off here, I cannot stay longer. I must go up again to my own people."</p>
    <p>Frau Holle said, "You are right, and because you have served me so <descriptor
            type="positive" gender="female">faithfully</descriptor>, I will take you back myself."
        With that she took her by the hand and <action agency="active" gender="female"
            willingness="eager">led her</action> to a large gate.</p>
    <p>The gate was opened, and while the girl was standing under it, an immense rain of gold fell,
        and all the gold stuck to her, so that she was completely covered with it. "This is yours
        because you have been so <descriptor type="positive" gender="female"
            >industrious</descriptor>," said Frau Holle.</p>
    <p>With that the gate was closed and the girl found herself above on earth. And as she entered
        the yard the rooster, sitting on the well, cried:</p>
    <p>She went home to her mother, and because she arrived all covered with gold, she was well
        received. The girl told all that had happened to her, and when the mother heard how she had
        come to the great wealth, she wanted to achieve the same fortune for the other, the <descriptor type="positive" gender="female"
        >ugly</descriptor> and
        <descriptor type="positive" gender="female"
            >lazy</descriptor> daughter. She made her go and <action agency="active" gender="female"
                willingness="eager">jump into the well</action>.</p>
    <p>Like the other girl, she too came to the beautiful meadow and walked along the same path.
        When she came to the oven, the bread cried again, "Oh, take me out. Take me out, or else
        I'll burn. I've been thoroughly baked for a long time."</p>
    <p>But the lazy girl answered, "As if I would want to get all dirty," and <action agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="neutral">walked away</action>.</p>
    <p>Soon she came to the apple tree. It cried out, "Oh, shake me. Shake me. We apples are all
        ripe."</p>
    <p>But she answered, "Oh yes, one could fall on my head," and with that <action agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="eager">she walked on</action>.</p>
    <p>When she came to Frau Holle's house, she was not afraid, because she had already heard about
        her <descriptor type="negative"
            gender="female">large teeth</descriptor>, and she immediately began to work for her. On the first day she forced
        herself, was <descriptor type="positive"
            gender="female">industrious</descriptor>, and obeyed Frau Holle, when she said something to her, because she
        was thinking about all the gold that she would give her. But on the second day she already
        began to be <descriptor type="negative"
            gender="female">lazy</descriptor>, on the third day even more so, and then she didn't even want to get up in
        the morning. She did not make the bed for Frau Holle, the way she was supposed to, and she
        did not shake it until the feathers flew. Frau Holle soon became tired of this and dismissed
        her of her duties. This was just what the lazy girl wanted, for she thought that she would
        now get the rain of gold.</p>
    <p>Frau Holle <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="neutral">led her</action> too to the gate. She stood beneath it, but instead of gold, a large kettle
        full of pitch spilled over her. "That is the reward for your services," said Frau Holle, and
        closed the gate.</p>
    <p>Then the lazy girl went home, entirely covered with pitch and did not come off as long as she lived.</p>
        <ending happy_ending="true"/>
    </body>
</fairytale>
