<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?xml-model href="../grimm_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<fairytale>
    <metadata>
        <title>The Robber Bridegroom</title>
        <author>Jacob and Wilhelm Grimm</author>
    </metadata>
    <body>
        <p>A princess had been promised in marriage to a prince. He asked her a number of times to
            visit him in his castle, <action agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="hesitant"
                >but she always declined,</action> because the way there led through a great forest,
            and she was afraid of getting lost.</p>
        <p>If that was her only concern, said the prince, then <action agency="active" gender="male"
                willingness="eager">he would help her by tying a ribbon to every tree, so that she
                could not lose her way.</action></p>
        <p><action agency="passive" gender="female" willingness="hesitant">For a while she attempted
                to further postpone her visit,</action> as though she were secretly afraid, but
            finally she ran out of excuses, and one day she had to go there. <action agency="active"
                gender="female" willingness="hesitant">She walked through deep, deep woods from
                morning until evening,</action> coming at last to a large house. Everything was
            quiet inside. There was only an <descriptor type="neutral" gender="female"
                >old</descriptor> woman there, sitting just outside the door.</p>
        <p>"Could you tell me if the prince, my bridegroom, lives here?"</p>
        <p>"My child," answered the woman, "it is a good thing that you arrived just now when the
            prince is not at home. I had to fill a large kettle with water, for they intend to kill
            you, cook you, and then eat you."</p>
        <p>Just then the prince and his band came home from their raid. However, because the
                <descriptor type="neutral" gender="female">old</descriptor> woman had sympathy with
            the <descriptor type="positive" gender="female">bride's youth and beauty,</descriptor>
            she said to her, before anyone noticed her, <action agency="active" gender="female"
                willingness="eager">"Quick, go down into the cellar and hide yourself</action>
            behind the large barrel!"</p>
        <p>The princess had hardly slipped behind the barrel when the band of robbers came into the
            cellar, bringing with them an <descriptor type="neutral" gender="female"
                >old</descriptor> woman= <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager"
                >whom they had captured.</action> From her corner the princess could see everything
            that was happening without herself being noticed, and she saw that the <descriptor
                type="neutral" gender="female">old</descriptor> woman was her grandmother. The
            robbers took the <descriptor type="neutral" gender="female">old</descriptor> grandmother
            and <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">murdered her.</action>
            Then <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">they took all the rings
                off her fingers,</action> one after the other. However, the ring from her ring
            finger would not come off, <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">so
                one of them picked up an ax and chopped off the finger.</action> The finger flew
            behind the barrel and fell right into the princess's lap.</p>
        <p>After the robbers had looked around for the finger for a long time, one of them said,
            "Did you look behind the large barrel?"</p>
        <p>"It would be better to wait until it's light to continue looking," said another. "We'll
            look tomorrow morning, and then we'll soon find the ring."</p>
        <p>After this <action agency="passive" gender="male" willingness="neutral">the band lay down
                to sleep there in the same cellar.</action> As soon as they were asleep and snoring,
                <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">the bride came out from
                behind the barrel.</action> They were all lying there in rows, and she would have to
            walk over all the sleeping men to reach the door. She carefully put her foot down
            between them, fearing always that she might awaken one of them, but fortunately that did
            not happen. After reaching the door she was once again in the woods, and because the
            moon shone brightly, <action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">she
                followed the ribbons until she arrived back home.</action></p>
        <p><action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">She told her father
                everything that had happened to her,</action> and <action agency="active"
                gender="male" willingness="eager">he immediately ordered an entire regiment to
                surround his castle,</action> as soon as the bridegroom arrived there. That
            happened. The <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">bridegroom came
                that very day and immediately asked why she hadn't come to visit him
                yesterday</action> as she had promised.</p>
        <p><action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">She said, "I had a very bad
                dream.</action> I dreamed that I went to a house. An <descriptor type="neutral"
                gender="female">old</descriptor> woman was sitting just outside the door, and she
            said to me, 'It is good that you came when no one is at home, for I have to tell you,
            that I had to fill a large kettle with water, and they intend to kill you, and boil you,
            and then eat you.' Even as she spoke, the robbers came home, and before anyone noticed
            me, the <descriptor type="neutral" gender="female">old</descriptor> woman said, <action
                agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">'Quick, go down into the cellar
                and hide yourself behind the large barrel.'</action> I was hardly there when <action
                agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">the robbers came down the cellar
                stairs. They were dragging</action> an <descriptor type="neutral" gender="female"
                >old</descriptor> woman with them, <action agency="active" gender="male"
                willingness="eager">whom they took hold of and murdered. After they had
                murdered</action> the <descriptor type="neutral" gender="female">old</descriptor>
            woman, <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">they began to pull all
                the rings off her fingers,</action> one after the other, but the ring on her ring
            finger wouldn't come off, so one of them <action agency="active" gender="male"
                willingness="eager">picked up an ax and chopped away at it until it</action> flew
            into the air, and it came down behind the barrel right into my lap, and here I have the
            finger!"</p>
        <p><action agency="active" gender="female" willingness="eager">With these words she suddenly
                pulled the finger from her pocket.</action></p>
        <p>When the bridegroom saw and heard these things <descriptor type="negative" gender="male"
                >he turned as white as chalk with fear.</descriptor>
            <action agency="active" gender="male" willingness="eager">He tried to flee by jumping
                out the window,</action> but the <action agency="active" gender="male"
                willingness="eager">sentries were standing below. They captured him and his entire
                band, and all of them were executed as a reward for their <descriptor gender="male"
                    type="negative">wicked</descriptor> deeds.</action></p>
        <ending happy_ending="true"/>
    </body>
</fairytale>
